Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ל"ו Lamed Vav
36. We pick up a little behind, only a little now. We
pick up on ל"ה עמוד ב', Lamed Hey Amud Bet, four lines
before the lines get wide. איתיביה Eisivya רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan לריש
לקיש. le-Reish Lakish. So there's a debate of the ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish and the... the משנה mishnah says that if חליצה chalitzah or
יבום yibbum was performed when the woman was pregnant, then to determine
whether or not it was valid will depend on whether the child,
whether she gives birth to a viable child or she miscarries. But
actually it seems that it would all be determined based on what
happened later, but actually you have a position of ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish that said that no, even if later the child is not
viable, a חליצה chalitzah done while she is pregnant is not a
valid חליצה. chalitzah. Because that actually was not stated in the משנה
mishnah and he said that a חליצה chalitzah would have to be
redone even if, even if she miscarried because the חליצה chalitzah was
done while she was pregnant. So now the גמרא Gemara picks up
the following. איתיביה Eisivya רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan לריש לקיש. le-Reish Lakish.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan challenged ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. אין הולד
של קיימא הוא אסור בקרובותיה והיא אסורה בקרוביו ופסולה מן הכהונה.
ein ha-vlad shel kayama hu assur bi-krovoteha ve-hi
assura bi-krovav u-psula min ha-kehuna. So now we're going to look at
the משנה. mishnah. The משנה mishnah says if the child is not
viable, a miscarriage let's say, then he is forbidden,
excuse me, this is the second part of the משנה, mishnah,
that if he go... wait, let me just check, I'm sorry,
one minute.
Right, right, right, okay, yes, okay. So if the child is not
viable and he did a, and he did a חליצה chalitzah while
she was pregnant. So if the child is not viable, therefore the
חליצה chalitzah was necessary, therefore it's a legitimate חליצה chalitzah presumably, and
for that reason she is... he is forbidden in her relatives because
she's his חלוצה chalutza which is like his גרושה. grusha. So she's...
he's forbidden in her relatives, she's forbidden in his relatives, right? ופסולה
מן הכהונה, u-psula min ha-kehuna, he's invalid for the... for the כהן.
kohen. So basically he has made her a חלוצה chalutza if it
turns out the child was not viable and therefore the חליצה chalitzah
was necessary. So
he said, בשלמא לדידי, bishlama ledidi, this is
good according to me, דאמינא, de-amina, חליצת מעוברת שמה
חליצה, chalitzat me'uberet shema chalitzah, חליצה chalitzah done when the woman is
pregnant is a good חליצה chalitzah if it turns out the child
isn't viable. משום הכי פסלה, mishum hachi pasla, that's why he invalidated
her for a כהן kohen because she becomes a חלוצה. chalutza. אלא
לדידך, ela ledidach,
but according to you, דאמרת, de-amart, חליצת מעוברת לא שמה חליצה, chalitzat
me'uberet lo shema chalitzah, חליצה chalitzah done when a woman is pregnant
isn't... isn't meaningful. אמאי פסלה מן הכהונה, amai pasla min ha-kehuna, why
did he invalidate her for a כהן? kohen? Why does he make
her into a חלוצה? chalutza? אמר ליה, amar lei, so ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish said back to him, מדרבנן miderabbanan ולחומרא. u-lechumra. Yeah, that's
רבנן. rabbanan. We can be מחמיר machmir that a חליצה chalitzah done
when a woman is pregnant is treated as a חליצה, chalitzah, but
it's not valid דאורייתא, de-oraita, and if it turns out that the
child isn't viable, she'll still require a חליצה chalitzah to free her,
okay? And he points out that the consequences in the משנה mishnah
are only stringencies. And what he's saying is it's very nice that
the משנה mishnah treats her as a חלוצה chalutza for all the
stringencies, but it was not a valid חליצה chalitzah to make her...
to free her and she still will require another
חליצה. chalitzah. Okay, ולחומרא בעלמא. u-lechumra be-alma. Okay. איכא דאמרי, ika de-amri,
some say that the
conversation went in the opposite way. איתיביה Eisivya ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
לרבי יוחנן. le-Rabbi Yohanan. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish challenged רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yohanan. אין הולד של קיימא הוא אסור
בקרובותיה והיא אסורה בקרוביו ופסולה מן הכהונה.
ein ha-vlad shel
kayama hu assur bi-krovoteha ve-hi assura bi-krovav u-psula min ha-kehuna. The same
line but he... but ריש לקיש Reish Lakish started with this to
prove his point. He said, look, all the consequences in the משנה
mishnah for a חליצה chalitzah done when the woman was pregnant were
חומרות, chumrot, were to make her forbidden to a כהן kohen or
to the relatives. בשלמא לדידי, bishlama ledidi, according to me it works,
דאמינא, de-amina, חליצת מעוברת לא שמה חליצה chalitzat me'uberet lo shema chalitzah
that it's not a legitimate חליצה chalitzah when she's pregnant. היינו דקתני
פסולה מן הכהונה, hainu de-katni psula min ha-kehuna, that's why the only
consequences are like she's invalid to כהנים, kohanim, לחומרא lechumra for the
stringency. ולא קתני אינה צריכה חליצה מן האחין. v'lo katni eina tzricha
chalitzah min ha-achin. It didn't tell you the bigger חידוש, chiddush, that
it was a legitimate חליצה chalitzah and now she doesn't need another
one after she miscarried. אלא לדידך, ela ledidach,
but according to you, אינה צריכה חליצה מן האחין מיבעי ליה. eina
tzricha chalitzah min ha-achin mibayei lei. Tell me the biggest חידוש, chiddush,
that a חליצה chalitzah done when she's pregnant if she miscarries, she
doesn't need another חליצה, chalitzah, she's free. So that's a good point.
Why didn't it tell me the קולא? kula? So he says back
to him, אמר ליה, amar lei, אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami,
you're right, it could... it should have said that. איידי דתני רישא
לא פסלה, aidi detani reisha lo pasla, but since the beginning of
the משנה mishnah said that when it was a... the child was
a viable child, that the act of חליצה chalitzah isn't even meaningful
לחומרא. lechumra. doesn't invalidate her to a כהן, Kohen, and that's a
big חידוש chiddush too, that when it turns out it was a
viable child, there's no חומרא. chumra. We treat it as if the
חליצה chalitzah didn't happen. We don't even apply any חומרות. chumrot. So
since that was the חידוש chiddush of the beginning of the משנה,
mishnah, תנא סיפא פסלה, tana seifa paslah, the end of the משנה
mishnah said that when it wasn't viable, she is invalid to a
כהן. Kohen. It said the חומרא, chumra, but you're right, it should
have gone further and it is true, she also wouldn't even need
another חליצה, chalitzah, it was totally legitimate. Okay, so you can work
either way in the משנה. mishnah. איתיבי רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש. Aiseiv
Rabbi Yochanan l'Reish Lakish. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is going to try
again. אין הולד שיהא קיים יקיים. Ein havalad she'hu kayam y'kayem. Okay,
if the child, this is a case where he went ahead and
he did יבום yibum when she was pregnant, and the same debate,
is it a legitimate יבום? yibum? Okay, so he went ahead and
did יבום yibum and then she miscarried. So he can stay married
to her. It's not a concern, right? Because then there was retroactively
there was a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum and it's not a
prohibition of אשת אח. eishet ach. Okay, so he stays married to
her.
That's when he did
יבום yibum instead of חליצה. chalitzah. אין הולד שיהא קיים יקיים. Ein
havalad she'hu kayam y'kayem. בשלמא לדידי דאמינא חליצת מעוברת שמה חליצה ביאת
מעוברת שמה ביאה Bi-shlama l'didi d'amina chalitzat m'uberet shmah chalitzah biat m'uberet
shmah biah that a חליצה chalitzah done to a pregnant woman is
legitimate if again in the end the child is not viable, or
a יבום yibum done is a legitimate יבום yibum if in the
end the child isn't viable. So according to me, משום הכי תני
יקיים. mishum hachi tani y'kayem. That's why it says the marriage you
know stay married. אלא לדידך דאמרת חליצת מעוברת לא שמה חליצה ביאת
מעוברת לא שמה ביאה, Ella l'didach d'amart chalitzat m'uberet lo shmah chalitzah
biat m'uberet lo shmah biah, but according to you that you said
the חליצה chalitzah wasn't good and the ביאה biah wasn't good when
she was pregnant,
so יחזור ויבם מיבעי ליה? yachzor v'yibom miba'lei? It shouldn't just say
stay married, it should say so far nothing has happened and if
you want to do יבום yibum and the child wasn't viable, go
do another יבום, yibum, go do the act again. Yeah right. So
that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. What do you
think's going to happen if they stay married? So the גמרא Gemara
is going to say so where were we, אלא, ella,
hold on, בשלמא לדידי דאמינא, bi-shlama l'didi d'amina, okay, so יבום מיבעי
ליה. yibum miba'lei. So the גמרא Gemara says no, מאי יקיים? mai
y'kayem? So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said back then what do you
think's going to happen if they stay married? What does it mean
stay married? יחזור ויבם ויקיים. Yachzor v'yibom v'ykayem. Okay, go ahead and
continue to have another act of sex and then that'll make you
הלכה halakhically married. Now he adds something, דלא סגי בלאו הכי, d'lo
sagi b'lav hachi, that there's no other choice. What does it mean
there's no other choice? He says look, according to me you got
yourself in a bit of a bind, which is that you've already
done ביאה, biah, but it's not yet, but you haven't yet done
יבום, yibum, right? So therefore according to me you really can't if
you know break it off at this stage. Okay, I mean רש"י
Rashi spells this out. Let me just show you the רש"י. Rashi.
רש"י Rashi
says דלא
סגי בלאו הכי d'lo sagi b'lav hachi about ten lines from the
bottom, דלא מיסתרא בלא ביאה לאחר שהפילה. d'lo mistra belo biah l'achar
she'hipilah. If you want now to divorce this woman or separate from
this woman, you have to first have sex and then give her
a גט. get. Okay, you're stuck sort of as it were. Why?
דאם לא יחזור ויבם לא מצי מיסתרא בגט. de-im lo yachzor v'yibom
lo matzi mistra b'get. You can't just give her a גט get
because the ביאה biah didn't count earlier.
ואין אדם יכול להוציא את יבמתו בגט אלא אם כן כנסה תחילה.
v'ein adam yachol l'hotzi et yevamto b'get ela im ken kinsah techilah.
וביאת מעוברת לאו שמה ביאה. u'biat m'uberet lav shmah biah. Okay, so
just do a חליצה chalitzah if יבום yibum earlier didn't count. ובחליצה
נמי לא מצי למיסתרא שהוא מכל מקום בעל. u'v'chalitzah nami lo matzi
l'mistra she'hu mi-kol makom ba'al. We can't allow a חליצה chalitzah to
follow sex with the sister-in-law, that obviously you know is completely inappropriate
at least at a rabbinic level even if that sex was did
not create יבום. yibum. So therefore ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is saying
is actually ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is saying according to me it
makes sense. Yes, for now the יבום yibum to become binding he
would have to have another act of sex. But actually when the
משנה mishnah says יקיים, y'kayem, it's not just saying you're allowed to
stay married, it's saying however you want to go forward here, whether
to keep the marriage or whether to divorce, you have to now
have sex. Okay, you have sex and that's an act of יבום
yibum and then after that you either can stay married or divorce,
but you can't do anything else now. You can't do חליצה, chalitzah,
you can't do a גט. get. The next thing that has to
happen is you have sex however you want to move forward. So
what's the, yeah. So alright, so that's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says. Okay. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say איתיבי ריש לקיש לרבי
יוחנן aiseiv Reish Lakish l'Rabbi Yochanan again, starting with this assumption ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish used this to prove his point again against רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אין הולד שיהא קיים יקיים. Ein havalad she'hu kayam
y'kayem. He did יבום yibum
and then the child wasn't viable, stay married. So בשלמא לדידי דאמינא
חליצת מעוברת לא שמה חליצה ביאת מעוברת לא שמה ביאה bi-shlama l'didi
d'amina chalitzat m'uberet lo shmah chalitzah biat m'uberet lo shmah biah according
to me the act didn't work until now. היינו דתני יקיים. hainu
d'tani y'kayem. That's what it means you can't you're allowed to stay
married, but you must go you know stay married at least for
initially. יחזור ויבם ויקיים. Yachzor v'yibom v'ykayem.
You first have to go back and have sex to make the
יבום yibum binding and then you can stay married or if you
want you can get divorced. דלא סגי בלאו הכי, d'lo sagi b'lav
hachi, there's no other choice. That's the first step that you have
to make. אלא לדידך Ella l'didach but according to you... יבום yibbum
already took effect, so why does it say יקיים yikayem which sounds
like you have to stay married? No, now you can choose. רצה
יוציא רצה יקיים. Ratza yotzi, ratza yikayem. If you want, you can
just give a גט get at this stage, you're already fully married.
מבעי ליה, Mibaei lei, that's what it should have said. So that's
not such a big question. אין הכי נמי, Ein hachi nami, of
course you could get divorced if you wanted to get divorced. But
I need to תני רישא יוציא, tani reisha yotzi, but since in
the case when the child was viable, it says you must get
divorced because obviously there it's your, you know, it's an ערווה, ervah,
it's a brother's wife, so תני נמי סיפא יקיים tani nami seiva
yikayem to stay married which means you're allowed to stay married. Okay.
So we have we can argue the משנה Mishnah both ways. מיתיבי,
Meitivei, I'll ask you. הכונס את יבמתו ונמצאת מעוברת. Hakones et yevimto
venimtzeit meuberet. הרי זו לא תינשא צרתה. Harei zo lo tinasei tzaratah.
So now we have a ברייתא braita that says the following: Somebody
has
does יבום yibbum with his sister-in-law and it turns out she was
pregnant. By the way, תוספות Tosafot points out, I'm not going to
do all the specifics for you, but points out that the משנה
Mishnah says that some cases say נמצאת מעוברת nimtzeit meuberet and some
say she was visibly מעוברת. meuberet. And you might have thought that
there might be a difference. Like you might have thought like it's
one thing to say חליצה chalitzah when it is discovered later she
was מעוברת meuberet is legitimate, but maybe if she was visibly מעוברת
meuberet at the time, right, then clearly that might be seen as
not legitimate because it was clear that she was pregnant. So תוספות
Tosafot points out that the ברייתות braitot move back and forth between
she was מעוברת meuberet and she was discovered to be מעוברת meuberet
that this debate of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan veResh Lakish
doesn't matter which scenario, even though obviously you could have theoretically made
a distinction between those two cases. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
tells like this. So here we have a
ברייתא. braita. Okay. Where are we?
מיתיבי. Meitivei. הכונס את יבמתו ונמצאת מעוברת. Hakones et yevimto venimtzeit meuberet.
Guy did יבום yibbum with his sister-in-law and then it turns out
that she was pregnant. הרי זו לא תינשא צרתה. Harei zo lo
tinasei tzaratah. Her sister-in-law, or her co-wife, cannot marry somebody else. Why?
שמא יהא הולד בן קיימא, Shema yehei havlad ben kayama, maybe the
child will be viable. Now this thinks about the scenario, right? You
have a question of Rachel and Devorah, no Rachel and Leah. Okay,
the guy does יבום yibbum with Rachel and turns out that Rachel
is pregnant. Can Devorah go ahead and marry somebody else? Well let's
think about the two scenarios. If Rachel, if the child is not
viable, and then it was a good act of יבום, yibbum, so
can Devorah go and marry somebody else after the act of יבום?
yibbum? Yes. If the child was viable, יבום yibbum wasn't necessary. Can
Devorah go ahead and marry somebody else? Yes, if יבום yibbum isn't
necessary then Devorah can. So what does the ברייתא braita mean, Devorah
don't marry somebody else until we because maybe the child won't be
viable? Who cares? Either way, either it was a good יבום yibbum
or יבום yibbum wasn't necessary. All right, so let's see. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, שמא יהא הולד בן קיימא, shema yehei
havlad ben kayama, maybe the child will be viable. So the גמרא
Gemara says what do you mean? Maybe the child's viable. If the
child's viable nobody needed יבום. yibbum. אדרבה, Adderaba, the opposite. כי הוי
הולד בן קיימא מיפטרה צרתה, Ki havei havlad ben kayama miptara tzaratah,
if the child was viable everyone's off the hook. So why can't
Devorah marry? אלא אימא שמא לא יהא הולד בן קיימא, Elah eima
shema lo yehei havlad ben kayama, it must mean that maybe the
child won't be viable. Okay, who cares there? It was a good
act of יבום. yibbum. Ah, was it a good act of יבום?
yibbum? It happened when she was pregnant. That maybe is the issue.
ואי סלקא דעתך ביאת מעוברת שמה ביאה, Ve-ei salka daitach biat meuberet
shemah biat, you רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan you think the act of
ביאה biat was good, אמאי לא תינשא צרתה, amai lo tinasei tzaratah,
so then it was a good act of יבום yibbum even if
she was pregnant, even if the child winds up being not viable.
So it was a good act of יבום. yibbum. So why can't
Devorah get married? תיפטר בביאה של חברתה, Tipater bebiat shel chavertah, let
her be exempt from that ביאה. biat. Either way, either ביאה biat
wasn't a need of יבום yibbum or it was a legitimate יבום.
yibbum. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so that seems to be a pretty
good proof. So this is going to lead אביי Abaye to reframe
the debate. Okay, we're going to reject אביי, Abaye, but let's just
see what אביי Abaye is going to say. You know what? אביי
Abaye said that's a pretty good proof. So בביאה כולי עלמא לא
פליגי דלא פטרה. Bebiat kulei alma lo pligi delo patra. Let's restate
it. When it comes to ביאה biat יבום yibbum with a woman
who's pregnant, everybody says that's not legitimate, which makes sense, right? Because
if she's pregnant, then we have to assume that that, you know,
the child might be viable, most of the time it is, and
therefore, you know, not only would יבום yibbum not be meaningful, it
would be a prohibition of אשת אח. eishet ach. So there to
say we cannot give any legitimacy to the act of ביאה, biat,
even if it turns out the child isn't viable, makes sense.
כולי עלמא לא פליגי דלא פטרה. Kulei alma lo pligi delo patra.
כי פליגי בחליצה. Ki pligi bachalitzah. They debate whether the חליצה, chalitzah,
because חליצה chalitzah anyway is separating the man and the woman, so
even though it might not be necessary if she's pregnant, at least
it could be legitimate.
It's a package deal.
All right, all right, all right. רבי יוחנן סבר חליצת מעוברת שמה
חליצה, Rabbi Yochanan savar chalitzat meuberet shemah chalitzah, that would work. ביאת
מעוברת לא שמה ביאה, Biat meuberet lo shemah biat, but he would
concede that the ביאה biat would not work. וריש לקיש סבר ביאת
מעוברת לא שמה ביאה, VeResh Lakish savar biat meuberet lo shemah biat,
the same way the sex wouldn't be an act of יבום, yibbum,
חליצת מעוברת לא שמה חליצה, chalitzat meuberet lo shemah chalitzah, the חליצה
chalitzah isn't. And that's why in this case, it assumes, oh, the
co-wife can't get married because maybe it
would be it wouldn't have been legitimate because she was still pregnant.
And everybody would agree that יבום yibum would not work once she
was pregnant. So that's אביי Abaye actually says maybe רב יוחנן Rav
Yochanan concedes that point. So now רבא Rava is going to say
back
what Michael just said. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, רבא Rava
said back, ממה נפשך, mamma nafshach, make up your mind. אי ביאה
מעוברת שמה ביאה, I biah meuberet shemah biah, if the ביאה biah
is good at this time, חליצת מעוברת שמה חליצה, chalitzat meuberet shemah
chalitza, the חליצה chalitza is good. ואי ביאה מעוברת לא שמה ביאה,
Ve'i biah meuberet lo shemah biah, and if the ביאה biah isn't
good, חליצת מעוברת נמי לא שמה חליצה, chalitzat meuberet nami lo shemah
chalitza, then the חליצה chalitza also won't be good. It's a package
deal, as Michael said. דהא קיימא לן, Deha kaima lan, we hold,
top of ל"ו עמוד א', lamed vav amud aleph, דכל העולה ליבום
עולה לחליצה, dechol ha'oleh leyibum oleh lechalitza, וכל שאינו עולה ליבום אינו
עולה לחליצה, vechol she'eino oleh leyibum eino oleh lechalitza,
that if יבום yibum is possible, חליצה chalitza is possible. If יבום
yibum isn't possible, then חליצה chalitza isn't. So, of course there are
exceptions to that, but we're assuming it's going to here be a
package deal. אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, so fine. So we're
back to our debate. They're debating both points. So how do you
deal with this issue of why can't דבורה Dvorah get married? Either
way, דבורה's Dvorah off the hook. אלא אמר רבא הכי קאמר, Ela
amar Rava hachi ka'amar, here's how you have to read that ברייתא.
braita.
הכונס יבמתו ונמצאת מעוברת, Hakones yevamto venimtzeit meuberet, a man does יבום
yibum with his sister-in-law, with שרה, Sarah, and it turns out she
was pregnant. הרי זו לא תינשא צרתה, Harei zu lo tinasei tzarata,
דבורה Dvorah shall not go get married. Why? שמא יהיה ולד בן
קיימא, Shema yihiyeh velad ben kayama, like the original גירסא, girsa, maybe
the child will be viable. That was the original גירסא girsa of
the ברייתא. braita. Okay, if the child's viable, everybody's off the hook.
Who cares if the child is viable? So if the child is
viable,
וביאת מעוברת לא שמה ביאה, uviat meuberet lo shemah biah, וחליצת מעוברת
לא שמה חליצה, vachalitzat meuberet lo shemah chalitza, okay, so the ביאה
biah didn't count, the חליצה chalitza didn't count, nothing counted, who cares,
the child was viable, everybody's off the hook? No. Now we're going
to introduce an important new idea. If the child is viable, when
are the women, are the wives free to remarry? Okay, only after
the child is born. Okay, so maybe the child will be viable,
good, who cares about the יבום yibum and חליצה? chalitza? They're going
to get off the hook. Yes, they'll get off the hook when?
ברם צא, Beram tzei, שמא יהיה ולד בן קיימא ולא שמה חליצה,
shema yihiyeh velad ben kayama velo shemah chalitza, שהולד אינה פוטר עד
שיצא לאוויר העולם, shehavelad einah poter ad sheyeitzei le'avir ha'olam, the child
does not get the wives off the hook until he is born.
Even later, that's after he's born.
Okay, well that'll be if to determine if he's viable or not.
But if you know he's viable, then it's the moment he's born.
We'll get to that later. So therefore, what he's saying is look,
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan could say that if it turns out not
viable, the ביאה biah and the חליצה chalitza count. But if it
turns out yes viable, there are two consequences. Everybody agrees the ביאה
biah and חליצה chalitza didn't count, but everybody also agrees that the
women aren't free, the wives aren't free until the child is born.
It's the birth, two things, because the child retrospectively was viable, the
חליצה chalitza and יבום yibum weren't meaningful, but even though they're not
meaningful, the woman is still not free from her past husband, as
it were, until the child is actually born. And that's why the
co-wife has to wait, because if there will be a viable child,
then חליצה chalitza and יבום yibum won't do the trick and you
have to wait until the child is born. Okay, so that's a
very important new principle.
תניא כוותיה דרבא, Tanya kevateih deRava, we taught a ברייתא braita like
רבא. Rava. הכונס יבמתו ונמצאת מעוברת, Hakones yevamto venimtzeit meuberet, a man
had sex with his sister-in-law and it turns out she was pregnant.
הרי זו לא תינשא צרתה, Harei zu lo tinasei tzarata, the co-wife
cannot get married. שמא יהיה ולד בן קיימא, Shema yihiyeh velad ben
kayama, lest it be a viable child, like our previous ברייתא braita
said. But now it spells out why that's an issue. ואין ביאה
וחליצה פוטרת, Ve'ein biah vachalitza poteret, and ביאה biah and חליצה chalitza
don't exempt in a case of a viable child. Everybody agrees to
that, even רב יוחנן. Rav Yochanan. אלא ולד פוטר, Ela velad poter,
it's the child that gets them off the hook. שהולד אינו פוטר
עד שיצא לאוויר העולם, Shehavelad eino poter ad sheyeitzei le'avir ha'olam, and
that doesn't get them off the hook until he is actually born.
Okay. So now, so now we've got a ברייתא braita that works
fine according to רב יוחנן. Rav Yochanan. So now the גמרא Gemara
says, טעמא דשמא יהיה ולד בן קיימא הוא, Taama deshama yihiyeh velad
ben kayama hu, so the reason דבורה Dvorah can't get remarried is
maybe the child will be viable and then you have to wait
till the child is born. הא לא הוי ולד בן קיימא, Ha
lo havi velad ben kayama, the ברייתא braita seems to imply that
if it's not a viable child, דבורה Dvorah would be allowed to
remarry. Okay. מפטר צרתה, Miftar tzarata, דבורה Dvorah could remarry if the
child weren't viable.
So this is now again a proof to רב יוחנן. Rav Yochanan.
לימא תהוי תיובתא דריש לקיש, Leima tehvei tiyuvta deResh Lakish, that should
be a challenge to ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. He did יבום yibum
with רחל. Rachel. The only problem is maybe it'll be a viable
child and you have to wait till the child's born. If it's
not a viable child, presumably דבורה Dvorah could remarry. Why could דבורה
Dvorah remarry? רחל's Rachel pregnant. Seems to be a proof like רב
יוחנן Rav Yochanan that a יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza done while
the woman is pregnant, if the child doesn't turn out to be
viable, is binding. So the גמרא Gemara says, so why not, so
it sounds like דבורה Dvorah could get married if the child won't
be viable.
תיובתא דריש לקיש, Tiyuvta deResh Lakish, that's a contradiction to ריש לקיש.
Resh Lakish. אמר לך ריש לקיש, Amar lach Resh Lakish, ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish will say to you, הכי קתני, Hachi katani, no,
here's how it's taught. הכונס יבמתו ונמצאת מעוברת *Hakones Yevamto Venimtza'at Me'uberet*,
if a guy has sex with his sister-in-law and turns out she
was pregnant, הרי זו לא תנשא צרתה *Harei Zu Lo Tinasei Tzaratah*.
The צרה *tzarah* can't get remarried for two reasons. Number one, in
scenario number one, שמא לא יהא הולד בן קיימא *shema lo yehei
havelad ben kayama*, maybe the child won't be viable, וחליצת מעוברת לא
שמה חליצה Halitza וביאת מעוברת לא שמה ביאה *vechalitzat me'uberet lo shemah
chalitza uvi'at me'uberet lo shemah bi'ah*, and the act of יבום yibum?
*Yibbum* will not have been meaningful. So that's on that side of
the possibility. She won't be able to be remarried because the יבום
yibum *Yibbum* was not meaningful. אם תאמר הולך אחר רוב נשים ורוב
נשים ולד מעליא ילדן *Im tomar holech achar rov nashim verov nashim
velad malya yalden*, and you'll say oh we don't have to worry
about that, most likely it'll be a viable kid and therefore they'll
be off the hook. No, ולד אינו פוטר עד שיצא לאויר העולם
*velad eino poter ad sheyetzei l'avir ha'olam*, that also you'll have to
wait until the child is born. So you're right, the ברייתא braisa
*Baraisa* only discussed the second scenario, that maybe it'll be viable, but
really the ברייתא braisa *Baraisa* is saying that either way, whether viable
or not viable, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish* is saying, דבורה
Devorah, *Devorah* cannot go and remarry. Not viable, the יבום yibum *Yibbum*
doesn't mean anything. Yes viable, you have to wait anyway until the
child is born.
Okay, so we still have the debate of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish.
*Reish Lakish* רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan, *Rebbi Yochanan* about whether it's meaningful
retroactively if the child isn't viable, but we have introduced the new
idea that if it is viable, nothing changes until the child is
born. Okay, אמר amar רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar *Amar Rebbi Elazar*, רבי
אלעזר Rebbi Elazar *Rebbi Elazar* said, אפשר איכא להדא דריש לקיש *Efsher
ika l'hada d'Reish Lakish*, is it possible? So far you know,
the indications I don't know, pretty evenly handed, but to me it
seems like it's pushing towards רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan. *Rebbi Yochanan*. Okay,
so he said and you know, so we're trying to now find
more explicit support for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish*. So רבי
אלעזר *Rebbi Elazar* said, is it possible that there would be this
opinion of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. *Reish Lakish* ולא תנן לה במתניתין
*velo tnan lah bematnitin* and there shouldn't be some משנה mishna *Mishna*
that gives it some support? It's an interesting assumption. So נפק דק
ואשכח *Nafak dak v'ashkach*, he went, he investigated, right, דק *dak* also
means like he paid close attention to the precise meaning of the
text and he discovered the following: דתנן d'tnan *Detnan*, we taught in
the later משנה mishna *Mishna*: האשה שהלך בעלה וצרתה למדינת הים *Ha'ishah
shehalach ba'alah vetzaratah limdinat hayam*. Okay, so רחל'ס *Rachel's* husband ראובן Reuven
*Reuven* there went with the co-wife דבורה Devorah *Devorah* and they went
to a faraway place. ובאו ואמרו לה *Uva'u v'amru lah* and they
came and said to her, מתו בעליך *metu ba'alayich* ראובן Reuven *Reuven*
died in Haiti. Okay, הרי זו לא תנשא *harei zu lo tinasei*.
So now what's דבורה Devorah *Devorah* supposed to do? Don't get married
ולא תתייבם *velo tityabbem* and don't get a יבום yibum *Yibbum* from
the brother. Why? Because until now there have been no kids. So
why not go ahead and do and get a יבום yibum *Yibbum*
from the brother or a חליצה Halitza *Chalitza* from the brother? Let's
investigate. Because עד שתדע שמא מעוברת היא צרתה *ad shetedah shema me'uberet
hi tzaratah*, maybe
לאה Leah *Leah* is pregnant. So don't go ahead and get remarried,
you don't know what לאה'ס *Leah's* story is. Maybe she's pregnant and
if she's pregnant then you can't go ahead and do יבום yibum
*Yibbum* with the brother because maybe it'll be a viable kid. You
can't go ahead and just marry another guy, right, because maybe it
won't be a viable child. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this: בשלמא יבומי לא *Bishlama yibumi lo*, I get why רחל Rachel
*Rachel* can't go ahead and do יבום yibum, *Yibbum* with the brother,
שמא יהא הולד בן קיימא *shema yehei havelad ben kayama*, maybe לאה
Leah *Leah* is pregnant and maybe it's a viable child ויפגע באיסור
אשת אח Eshet Ach. *veyifga be'issur eshet ach*, and then you're having
sex with a brother's wife, right, because then there's no מצוה *mitzvah*
of יבום yibum *Yibbum* if לאה Leah. *Leah* is pregnant with a
viable child. דאורייתא d'Oraita *De'oraisa*, biblically. אלא לא תחלוץ *Ela lo tachlotz*,
why can't she get חליצה Halitza *Chalitza*? Now the ברייתא braisa *Baraisa*
never said she can't get חליצה Halitza *Chalitza*, it said don't get
remarried, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes what that means is don't
get חליצה Halitza *Chalitza* in order to get remarried. Okay, so why
can רחל Rachel *Rachel* not get a חליצה Halitza, *Chalitza* and then
get remarried? אמאי *Amai*? That should work either way. Either there's no
pregnancy, no viable child and therefore the חליצה Halitza *Chalitza* works, or
there is a pregnancy, a viable child and therefore you don't need
חליצה Halitza *Chalitza*. Similar type of a question, right? Why can't you
get חליצה Halitza, *Chalitza*? בשלמא *Bishlama*, now we've already introduced the idea
of here's the possible problem: that לאה Leah? *Leah* is pregnant, it
will be viable and therefore you have to wait until the child
is born. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says fine, and I could
get why you might have to wait nine months to make sure
that if there was a child, the child would have been born
by now. Okay, but why do you have to wait... why can
you never go ahead and do it? Okay, so it goes like
this. אלא נחזי *Ela nechzei*, let's take a look. אמאי בשלמא תחלוץ
בתוך תשעה ותנשא בתוך תשעה לא *Amai bishlama tachlotz betoch tishah vetinasei
betoch tishah lo*, I get that you can't have חליצה Halitza *Chalitza*
during nine months and get married during nine months. היינו ספק Safek.
*Hainu safek*, that's the question: maybe it's a viable child and the
child won't have been born yet. אלא תחלוץ בתוך תשעה *Ela tachlotz
betoch tishah*, but why not do this? Get your חליצה Halitza *Chalitza*
right away ותנשא לאחר תשעה *vetinasei l'achar tishah* and go ahead and
get remarried after nine months? Right? So either way, either you got
your חליצה Halitza, *Chalitza* and that was okay, or it was a
viable child and now you can get remarried. So since it doesn't
give that option, it must be that the חליצה Halitza, *Chalitza* she
would have gotten during the nine months wouldn't have been good because
at that time לאה *Leah* was pregnant. pregnant, okay? At that time
whatever, whoever it was, דבורה Devorah was pregnant. So therefore, right? So
therefore that is a proof to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish. right? People
sort of with me or have I got you lost here?
Use the board for a sec, okay?
Here's רחל Rachel at home, okay? Here
are, here's
the far away island with her husband ראובן Reuven and the co-wife,
okay? So
here's ראובן Reuven and דבורה, Devorah okay? Now ראובן Reuven died. Okay,
we don't know if דבורה is pregnant, okay? So if she's pregnant,
she right? If she's pregnant
with a viable child, right, then she has to wait nine months,
right? If דבורה is pregnant with a viable child, right? Because then
you're going to have to, then she's only off the hook after
the child is born, okay? And for all she knows, right, לאה
became pregnant the minute before, you know, ראובן Reuven died. Okay, if
she's either not pregnant or not viable, then she can get go
ahead right away and do חליצה halitza or ייבום, Yibum, okay? So
ייבום Yibum we're not going to do because obviously it might be
this scenario and then you're going to have ייבום Yibum with אשת
אח. Eshet Ach.
But why not
go ahead and do חליצה halitza right away, okay? And after nine
months go ahead and get married and then you've played it safe,
okay? So he says since it didn't give that option, it must
be that חליצה halitza right away won't work because maybe דבורה is
pregnant and the חליצה halitza won't work as long as she is
pregnant. So that proves like ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Now that's a
pretty weak proof because as the גמרא's Gemara going to say, so
just do the חליצה halitza, and the remarry after nine months. You
haven't really answered your question, right? That should still be an option.
Fine, wait nine months, then do חליצה, chalitza then get remarried, right?
So either way you have the question.
When you're saying רחל Rachel get remarried or she can't get remarried,
you're talking about to another brother? No.
No, she can never marry another brother because it might be that
there's a viable child and it's אשת אח. eishet ach. But חליצה
chalitza. and let her get married to somebody unrelated, yeah exactly. All
right.
So the so so he says since you didn't give the option
of doing חליצה chalitza right away and then marrying after nine months,
proves like ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish. it wouldn't have worked. It's a
pretty weak proof. The גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא תחלוץ ותנשא
לאחר תשעה. Ela tachalot v'titnasay l'achar tisha. So
גמרא Gemara says לטעמיך, L'taimach, that's a question? So according to you,
let's work with ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. You still don't understand it.
אלא תחלוץ ותנשא לאחר תשעה. Ela tachalot v'titnasay l'achar tisha. Wait until
after nine months, do חליצה, chalitza, get remarried, right? It still doesn't
explain why this woman is stuck. Just wait nine months, do חליצה
chalitza. and get remarried according to everybody that should work. אלא בר
מיניה דהיא. Ela bar minai d'hi.
Don't wor—like let
exclude that case. That's not relevant. Why not? דאביי בר אבין ורב
חננא בר אביי D'Abaye bar Avin v'Rav Chinana bar Abaye or אבין
Avin דאמרי תרוייהו, d'amri taryayhu, they both say, שמא יהא ולד בן
קיימא ונמצא אתה מצריכה כרוז לכהונה. shema yei vlad ben kayama v'nimtza
ata matricha kruz likhuna.
Here's the reason. The reason that we don't do חליצה chalitza here
is not because we can't figure out how to get רחל Rachel
remarried. It's easy. You wait nine months, you do חליצה, chalitza you
get remarried, it works according to everyone. There's only one problem. What's
going to happen if she does חליצה, chalitza, gets remarried, and then
it turns out that דבורה had a viable child? So then the—she's
not a חלוצה, chalutza, right? The חליצה chalitza wasn't meaningful. Well, she
wants that status removed because now she's going to be אסור assur
to a כהן. Kohen. So now you're going to have to make
a big public announcement, right? You know like sometimes when they do—I'm
sorry to give this example but okay—but you know like they do
like כשרות kashrus alert? You know, the OUs that are appearing on
this product are—were—mistake. So they're going to have to do a חליצה
chalitza alert. The fact that רחל Rachel got חליצה chalitza was a
mistake, she's not a חלוצה, chalutza, they'll make a big announcement. And
we don't—we don't want to do that because, you know, whenever you
print a retraction in the newspaper, nobody sees the retraction, right? So
people will think she's a חלוצה, chalutza, she's not a חלוצה, chalutza,
and it'll lead to all this confusion. So therefore we don't want
her—even though חליצה chalitza. will work, we don't want to do it
because we might have to reverse it. And therefore we'd like to
first figure out what the story is with לאה before we move
forward here. Okay, so that's what they say. Okay, ולצרכה—so v'litzricha גמרא
Gemara says ולצרכה, v'litzricha, so what,
so make the announcement? No. דילמא איכא איניש דהוי בחליצה, dilma ika
inish d'havi b'halitza, somebody who was at the חליצה, chalitza ולא הוי
בהכרזה, v'lo havi b'achraza, didn't see the announcement, didn't see the retraction.
And now what will happen? רחל will go ahead and marry a
כהן. Kohen. ואתי למימר קשרי חלוצה לכהונה. V'asai l'maymar kashari chalutza l'khuna.
Look, this woman's a חלוצה, chalutza, she's marrying a כהן. Kohen.
So we don't want to get into that area of confusion. Let's
first clarify figure out what's going on with לאה. So interesting, you
know, you would not have had so many סוגיות sugyas in the
גמרא Gemara if they had had cell phones, you know, or instant
communication. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said,
one minute. מידי לא תחלוץ ולא—אביי said there's a much simpler answer
to this case. מידי לא תחלוץ ולא. Midi lo tachlot v'lo לא
תנסב ולא תתייבם תני. Lo tinasev v'lo tisyabem tani. Did the משנה
mishna. say she can't get חליצה chalitza and she can't get יבום?
Yibum That's not what the ברייתא braisa said. The ברייתא braisa just
said לא תנסב ולא תתייבם תני. Lo tinasev v'lo tisyabem tani. She
can't do יבום Yibum. and she can't just סתם stam marry another
guy, but it didn't say she can't get חליצה. chalitzah So now
it all makes sense. Why can רחל not get יבום Yibum until
she knows what happened with לאה? Because maybe there's a viable child.
Why can't she go ahead and marry another guy without חליצה Chalitza,
straight? Maybe there's no viable child and she needs חליצה, Chalitza. right?
All it says is don't do יבום and don't סתם stam marry
another guy. It never said she can't get חליצה. Chalitza. Get חליצה
Chalitza and go ahead, wait nine months and do it and remarry.
Very carefully.
Exactly, exactly. Good point because he was דתי, dos, but he wasn't
so דתי. dos. Okay, לא תנסב ולא תתייבם תני, Lo tinasev v'lo
tisyabem tani, בלא חליצה. belo chalitza.
It means without חליצה Chalitza, she can't do those things. אבל אי
חליץ לה, Aval ee chalitz lah, if you want to do חליצה,
Chalitza הכי נמי דשריא, hachi nami desharya, it would be okay. So
there's no משנה Mishnah. that supports ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. And so
we're back to the debate of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש. Rebbi Yochanan
v'Reish Lakish. תניא כוותיה דריש לקיש. Tanya k'vasei d'Reish Lakish. Ah, at
least we got a ברייתא Baraita. like ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. החולץ
למעוברת, HaCholetz l'Meuberet,
explicitly this case. חליצה Chalitza? done to a pregnant woman, והפילה, v'hipila,
and she miscarried, צריכה חליצה מן האחים, tzricha chalitza min ha'achim, she
still needs to get another חליצה Chalitza to free her. Okay, even
though חליצה Chalitza was done, that was not binding and she needs
another חליצה. Chalitza So that's at least a ברייתא Baraita. like ריש
לקיש. Reish Lakish אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says
רבא, Rava, הלכתא כוותיה דריש לקיש. Hilchasa k'vasei d'Reish Lakish. We rule
like ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. I thought this was a surprise because
at least to me it sounded more like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan
but we at least have a ברייתא braita, in the end like
ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish We rule like ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. חליצה
Chalitza, done when the woman is pregnant is not binding. And actually
that actually creates a nice if you would parallel, right? Because, and
you know, it could be interesting when it's not parallel, but it's
also interesting when it is parallel, right? She's pregnant. If it winds
up being viable, then it doesn't happen until the child is born.
Even if it winds up being not viable, nothing can happen while
she's pregnant. So in both scenarios, while she's pregnant, right, everything is
in abeyance, right? Whether it's going to be a viable child, that
will need for the child to be born, whether it won't be
a viable child, יבום or חליצה Chalitza won't work while she's pregnant.
So nothing happens while, nothing binding, effective happens while she's pregnant.
Yes, I had two questions. One is just simply literary. רבי אלעזר
lived after רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש. Rebbi Yochanan v'Reish Lakish.
Yeah, there's a רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer that was a תנא, tanna,
רבי אלעזר is an אמורא. amora. Okay.
Would modern technology...
Okay, so that's a question. Yeah, so that's a question about which
we'll get to also in general about having to worry maybe she
is pregnant, right? Or viability.
Viability's an interesting question. I mean you, as I, right, like I
guess sometimes you know that the fetus is totally not viable and
right and...
I know, but he's saying the opposite. That knowing it is viable
obviously yes, God forbid something could happen, but let's say you know
that the fetus isn't viable and won't survive even the duration of
the pregnancy, right? Does that then... that's an interesting question. Presumably yes,
but the פוסקים poskim definitely deal with those questions in terms of
contemporary applications. Like do you have to wait because she might be
pregnant? So the גמרא Gemara would say wait three months to determine
whether she's pregnant or not. How about just take a pregnancy test?
So that definitely comes up a lot in the פוסקים. poskim. Okay,
so let's take a look. We rule like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish.
בהני תלת, bhani telat, in the following three cases, even though normally
we rule like רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan חדא הא דאמרן, Chada ha
d'amran, one this issue. While she's pregnant, nothing happens. Viable won't work,
not viable won't work, nothing happens while she's pregnant. Number one. Number
two, אידך, idach, דתנן detnan, in the משנה. Mishna Now these next
two cases are going to have nothing to do with יבמות. Yevamos.
It's cases we פסקן pasken like ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish המחלק נכסיו
על פיו, HaMichalek nechasav al piv,
somebody is on his deathbed and basically giving out his property, right?
It's a deathbed bequest, a type of a will. He's distributing his
property. Right now, but he's actually what he's actually doing is redistributing
the inheritance with his children. ריבה לאחד ומיעט לאחד, Riba l'echad u'mi'at
l'echad, he gives a bigger portion to one child, a smaller portion
to another, השוה להן את הבכור, hishva lahen et ha'bechor, or let's
say he says the בכור, bechor, the firstborn, gets an equal portion,
not a double portion, דבריו קיימין, devarav kayamin, that actually works. Now
that you should say what do you mean that works? The תורה
Torah says you can't, you know, give the בכור bechor portion to
another person, to another child. But the point is he's doing this
as a bequest. He's doing this as a gift,
מתנה, matana, not
claiming that it's a ירושה. yerusha. So he's doing it like as
a will and as a gift, and not as a ירושה, yerusha,
and therefore he can reapportion which child gets how much. That works.
ואם אמר משום ירושה, V'im amar mishum yerusha, but if he said,
no, ראובן Reuven, will, his inheritance will be, you know, so big,
and שמעון's Shimon inheritance will be so big, that won't work because
he's making it, he's changing what it means as an inheritance. So
לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, he didn't say anything. Now כתב
בין בתחילה בין בסוף בין באמצע משום
מתנה, Kasav bein b'tchila bein b'sof bein b'emtza mishum matana, it's interesting
he switches from saying to writing, we're not going to worry about
that, but let's assume it was a written document. And he adds
the word מתנה matana in there somewhere, whether it's at the beginning,
middle, or end, דבריו קיימין. devarav kayamin. So let's say he said,
ראובן Reuven shall inherit this portion and have it as a gift.
Or behold I am giving to ראובן, Reuven even if he said
it as a verb, behold I am giving to ראובן Reuven or
it should be given to ראובן Reuven this inheritance. So as long
as there's the word gift or giving somewhere in there, it's going
to work and we'll treat it as a gift and not as
a bequest, which is quite fascinating. In general, we'll get to
whatever, like three years from now we'll get to בבא בתרא Bava
Batra and we'll deal with this, but we see that the rabbis,
although the Torah says you cannot change the inheritance, the rabbis created
deathbed bequests and they created wills and they created all these ways
in which the inheritance can be reapportioned. And here, even if you
say both languages, inheritance and gift, we'll read the language, we'll give
gift as the dominant language to make it valid.
Okay, now.
Yeah, in that scenario. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, לעולם לא
קנה עד שיאמר פלוני ופלוני יירשו שדה פלוני. le'olam lo kana ad
sheyomar ploni uploni yirshu sde ploni. It doesn't work unless you say
ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon should inherit this field, פלוני ופלוני ploni
uploni should inherit field A and field B, meaning ראובן Reuven? field
A, שמעון Shimon field B, שנתתים להם במתנה לירושה shenatatim lahem bematana
liyerusha that I have given them in a gift for an inheritance.
Now what's he adding? You have a language of מתנה matana mixed
with a language of ירושה. yerusha. So what he's actually discussing, which
isn't clear here, is a scenario not mentioned, not addressed in this
mishna. Let's say the father says I am giving,
ראובן Reuven shall inherit field A and שמעון Shimon shall receive as
a gift field B, or I'm giving שמעון Shimon field B. So
שמעון Shimon gets field B, it's a gift. What do you say
about ראובן? Reuven So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no, by ראובן
Reuven he used the language ירושה yerusha and therefore
ראובן Reuven. is stuck, right? Hold on, let me just make sure
I got this right.
Oh I'm sorry, no the opposite. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says since
he has the language of מתנה matana for one of the brothers,
it works even for the other brother. So even though he said
let ראובן Reuven get it as an inheritance and שמעון Shimon get
it as a gift, we use the language of gift for שמעון
Shimon to interpret the language of inheritance for ראובן. Reuven Very liberal
in trying to make it always work as a gift. ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish says no, it will not work unless you bundle it
together. If you say ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon let them get
a gift and an inheritance, then it works. But if you separate
them and you say let ראובן get an inheritance and let שמעון
Shimon get a gift, שמעון's Shimon part works for שמעון, Shimon, ראובן
is out in the cold because there you used language of ירושה.
yerusha. And there we rule like ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish So that's
number two where we rule like ריש לקיש.
Reish Lakish, What do you mean
by
out in the cold? He doesn't get, he doesn't get it because
he tried to, you can't verbally change, you can't change a ירושה.
yerusha. Oh he wasn't supposed to על פי התורה. al pi haTorah.
He gets his normal ירושה yerusha but he doesn't get based on
what this guy said. Right. Yeah.
Maybe it was an extra share or something and ירושה yerusha about
like if the father loves this other child more even though he's
not the firstborn so allowing him to...
Exactly,
that's what I was saying, that the rabbis although the Torah seems
to feel like you're fixed in the way that the Torah dictates
it, the rabbis created all these devices to allow reapportionment. Okay, ואידך,
ve'idach, that's number two. And the third, דתנן,
this is a famous debate of רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan
veReish Lakish throughout ש"ס Shas which we're about to see. הכותב כל
נכסיו לבנו לאחר מותו. hakotev kol nechasav livno le'achar moto. A father
says I am giving to my son this field starting now but
to be
completed after I die. Now what does that mean? How does he
get the field now and fully get it after you die? So
the rabbis say the way we interpret that to mean is that
the title transfers now but until I'm still alive I still get
the benefit from it, I still get the פירות. peirot. And he
will only get the פירות peirot the benefit, right, it's called usufruct,
right? He will only get that after I die. Okay? So that
means while the father is alive the son has what's called קנין
הגוף kinyan haguf title and the father has קנין פירות kinyan peirot
the right to usage. Okay and then that's what he says. So
what does the mishna tell us? האב אינו יכול למכור מפני שנתן
לבן. ha'av eino yachol limkor mipnei shenatan laben.
The father can't sell the field because he already transferred title to
the son.
והבן אינו יכול למכור מפני שהן ברשות האב vehaben eino yachol limkor
mipnei shehen birshut ha'av because the father still has control over the
fruit. Now they're not supposed to. Let's say they went ahead and
did it.
מכר האב machar ha'av if the father went ahead and sold it
after he transferred title, מכורין עד שימות. mechurin ad sheyamut. At least
he can sell, what does the father have? The father has the
usufruct, he has the fruit, he has the benefit for the field.
He can sell not the title but he can transfer what he
has. He can at least transfer his right to the usage of
the field and the fruit as long as he's alive because that's
exactly the rights that he has. That he can transfer. מכורין עד
שימות. mechurin ad sheyamut. The use of the field is sold. until
he dies. מכור עד
שימות Machur ad sheyamut too, until he dies. מכר הבן, Machar haben,
if the son sells it. Now the son has a title that
right now doesn't mean anything, that right now doesn't give him any
use. So what will happen if the son sells it? אין לו
כח כלום עד שימות האב. Ein lo koach klum ad sheyamut ha'av.
Right now the purchaser gets nothing cause the son has nothing. But
once the father dies, then the son gets the right of the
fruit. Since the son sold somebody everything he owned in the field,
so when that translates also into the right of the fruit, the
benefit of the field, it then also transfers to the person he
sold it to. Okay, and at that moment the purchaser gets everything.
Okay, so that's nice. But now how about the following scenario? ואיתמר,
Ve'itmar, it was taught. What happens if מכר הבן בחיי אב, machar
haben bechayei av, the son sold it. Now we understand what happens
when the father's gonna die. But here's what happens. ומית הבן בחיי
אב. Umayta ben bechayei av. But the son died first. Okay, so
when the father eventually dies, the son isn't around to claim his
use of the fruit that through him can transfer to the purchaser,
right? If he's around, it goes to him and through him to
the guy who purchased it. But he's not around, what's the story?
Okay, so was the sale a meaningful sale if he sold the
title when he didn't have rights to the fruit? Okay, is that
enough of an ownership of a title to genuinely transfer title? Okay,
and if it is, then when the father dies and the father
removes himself from the picture, whoever owned the title will get the
right to the fruit. So was the son able to sell the
title when it was under the control of the father? So רבי
יוחנן אמר לא קנה לוקח. Rabbi Yochanan amar lo kana lokeach. No,
it didn't transfer. If the son's alive and the father dies, then
everything happens then. But if the son is dead, then that sale
at that time was meaningless, cause the father had right of the
fruit, so the son's sale of the title was meaningless. ריש לקיש
אמר קנה לוקח, Reish Lakish amar kana lokeach, it was meaningful. רבי
יוחנן אמר לא קנה לוקח, Rabbi Yochanan amar lo kana lokeach, here's
the logic. קנין פירות כקנין הגוף דמי. Kinyan peirot kekinyan haguf dami.
The father's right of the fruit gives him a title to the
field. And therefore if the father at the time that he was
alive was considered the owner of the field, even though technically the
son had the title, the son's sale was meaningless. The son's sale
was meaningless at that time, it will only be meaningful if the
father dies before the son when everything reverts to the son. But
at that moment it was meaningless, cause as long as the father
had קנין פירות, kinyan peirot, therefore the father was the one who
was seemed to have the title. ריש לקיש אמר קנה לוקח, Reish
Lakish amar kana lokeach, no, even at that time it was a
legitimate transfer of title. קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף דמי. Kinyan peirot
lav kekinyan haguf dami. The father's right to the fruit does not
make the father considered the title holder, the son was the title
holder and the son could transfer title even while the father still
has right to the fruit. Okay, and this is the major debate
of ריש לקיש and רבי יוחנן through ש"ס, Shas, קנין פירות כקנין
הגוף דמי kinyan peirot kekinyan haguf dami or לאו כקנין הגוף דמי.
lav kekinyan haguf dami. It's a fascinating סוגיא sugya which the גמרא
develops elsewhere, but here what you need to know, we פוסקים pasken
like ריש לקיש that it says לאו כקנין הגוף דמי. lav kekinyan
haguf dami. And the son is seen as the title holder and
not the father. Okay, great! Now let's move on. That was the
debate of רבי יוחנן and ריש לקיש about what happens with חליצה
and יבום when the woman is pregnant. And we פוסקים pasken like
ריש לקיש, nothing happens when she's pregnant. Even if you do it,
it wasn't binding. אין הולד של קיימא. Ein havlad shelo kayama. Now
going to the second part of the משנה. If
you did יבום, it turns out the child was not viable, so
the יבום was good and stay married. Okay. תנא משום רבי אליעזר.
Tana mishum Rabbi Eliezer. תנא, Tana, we taught in a ברייתא. braita.
משום רבי אליעזר אמרו, Mishum Rabbi Eliezer amru, they said in the
name of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, יוציא בגט. yotzi beget. Whoa! Might
be that retroactively it was okay, but he wasn't how could we
tolerate the fact that he had sex with this woman when she
was pregnant? In all likelihood it was going to be a viable
child. In all likelihood this would have been an איסור ערוה isur
ervah of אשת אח. So even if retroactively it all works out,
we're going to demand a divorce. We can't even post-facto tolerate the
fact that he had sex with his sister-in-law when she was pregnant
and might very well have been an איסור ערוה. isur ervah. יוציא
בגט. Yotzi beget. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא. Rava. רבי מאיר
ורבי אליעזר אמרו דבר אחד. Rabbi Meir veRabbi Eliezer amru davar echad.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say the same
thing. Not literally, but it means both of them feel that when
somebody goes ahead and gets married when he shouldn't have gotten married,
even if it all works out okay, we're going to demand a
גט. get. We can't tolerate it and we're going to demand a
גט. get. So let's take a look. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer הא
דאמרין, had'amarin, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer we just said. ורבי מאיר דתניא,
VeRabbi Meir detanya, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who we taught in the
ברייתא. לא ישא אדם עוברת חברו ומיניקת חברו. Lo yisa adam uberet
chaveiro umeyneket chaveiro. A man should not marry his
friend's pregnant wife and nursing wife. Now obviously his friend is no
longer married to this woman, okay, but a man divorces a woman
or dies, he leaves over a widow or divorcee who is pregnant
or nursing, this woman should not get another man should not marry
her during this stage. Why not? Because you might remember we learned
before. or that if a woman gets pregnant while she is nursing
or while she is pregnant, it is seen as a סכנה. sakana.
Okay, now of course you know why does it say specifically another
man? Maybe even the in general with the woman's with her husband,
she shouldn't be getting pregnant during this time and using birth control
etc. So the answer is אינה הכי נמי, ina hachi nami, but
we're just more concerned that the second husband won't be as sensitive
to those issues. The גמרא later will discuss it. So, a man
should not marry a woman who is pregnant or nursing from a
previous marriage. All right? ואם נשא יוציא v'im nasa yotzi and if
he went ahead and married her, he has to divorce her or
separate, we'll see about that in a minute. ולא יחזיר עולמית v'lo
yachazir olamit דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. And he can never
remarry her. We are so careful that he doesn't violate this that
even בדיעבד bedi'eved we'll demand that they get divorced and never get
remarried. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. וחכמים אומרים יוציא. v'Chachamim
omrim yotzi. No, no, no. Fine, initially get divorced or separate, fine.
וכשיגיע זמנו לכנוס uch'sheyagia zmano lichnos when it's time then to get
married, she stops nursing and at that stage he has the baby
and stops nursing, יכנוס yichnos then let them get remarried. Okay, so
you see רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is very strict. Okay, and here
too it's a similar idea to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, did something
he shouldn't have done, get divorced. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei
Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, you can't throw them all in the
same category. ממאי? mimai? How do you know it's the same position?
דילמא לא היא, dilma lo hi, maybe that's not true. עד כאן
לא קאמר רבי אליעזר הכא, ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Eliezer hacha,
why did רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say here they have to get
divorced? אלא משום דקפגע באיסור אשת אח דאורייתא. ela mishum d'kapga b'issur
eshet ach d'Oraita. He's having sex with his brother's pregnant wife, that
could be an איסור כרת issur kares in the תורה. Torah. That's
very serious. Okay, thank God it worked out not that way, but
it could have been. We're not going to tolerate that even
בדיעבד. bedi'eved. אבל התם דרבנן, aval hatam derabbanan, it's only a דרבנן
derabbanan prohibition of that scenario of marrying a nursing woman. דרבנן סבירא
ליה, derabbanan sevira lei, he'll hold like the רבנן, Rabbanan, get remarried,
fine. אי נמי, i nami, so okay, it's a big difference דאורייתא
d'Oraita to דרבנן. derabbanan. Or I'll say the opposite. אי נמי, i
nami, עד כאן לא קאמר רבי מאיר התם, ad kan lo ka'amar
Rabbi Meir hatam, maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is only very strict
in that
case, אלא משום דרבנן, ela mishum derabbanan, because it's דרבנן. derabbanan. And
because it's דרבנן derabbanan he's afraid people will treat it lightly. וחכמים
עשו חיזוק לדבריהם יותר משל תורה. v'Chachamim asu chizuk l'divreihem yoteir m'shel
Torah.
The רבנן Rabbanan said to be especially stringent on their rules because
more than on the דאורייתא because people will treat it lightly. אבל
הכא, aval hacha, but if it's an issue of a concern of
a brother's wife, מדאורייתא, mid'Oraita, that's a biblical איסור כרת. issur kares.
מיפרש פרישו מינה, mifrash prishu minah, so anyway people will naturally not
do it and we don't have to be so strict if one
idiot went ahead and violated, we don't have to think that we're
going to have to go ahead and make a terrible
demand, stringent demand. It's not going to lead to other people. People
keep away from it. Okay,
so that's interesting seeing some parallel but pointing out that the cases
are different. Now we're going to look at this case about what
happens in this scenario of marrying a woman who is nursing or
pregnant. אמר so, and the language was יוציא, yotzi, right? Now רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir was clear, יוציא yotzi presumably and never get remarried
means get a divorce, that's the end of the story. But for
the חכמים Chachamim who allow them to get together after, get back
together after she stops nursing, what did they mean when they said
יוציא? yotzi? Did they mean separate or do they mean divorce? All
right, so let's take a look. Very good, let's take a look.
So אמר רבא, amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, ולדברי חכמים, ul'divrei Chachamim,
according to the חכמים, Chachamim, יוציא בגט. yotzi b'get. You actually mean
literally get a divorce with a גט. get. And as Michael of
course points out, that's not a trivial matter at all. It makes
her גרושה, gerusha, it means that if the husband is a כהן,
kohen, they can't divorce and get remarried. אמר מר זוטרא, amar Mar
Zutra, דיקא נמי, dika nami, that also can be read by, seen
by a close reading of the language. דקתני, d'katani, the משנה says
יוציא. yotzi. It says divorce, right? Take... remove. ולא קתני יפריש, v'lo
katani yafrish, it doesn't say separate, it says take, literally take her
out, but that means divorce, that's the word used for divorce. שמע
מינה, shma minah, that is a good close reading of the text.
Now אמר ליה, amar lei, so we're going to get to the
question of כהן. kohen. Would you really demand this even in the
case of כהן? kohen? So that's what the גמרא is going to
get to. אמר ליה רב אשי לרב הושעיא בריה דרב אידי. amar
lei Rav Ashi l'Rav Hoshaya brei d'Rav Idi. So רב אשי Rav
Ashi said to רב הושעיא, Rav Hoshaya, התם תנן, hatam tnan, this
is going to be a lead up to the כהן kohen question
which Michael was asking. It's very nice to say גט. get. Would
you say it by a כהן? kohen? So let's take a look.
Over there we taught, or actually ברייתא, we taught in a ברייתא.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר כל ששהה באדם שלשים יום אינו נפל.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer kol she-shaha b'adam shloshim yom einu nefel.
Okay, this gets to this question that we were talking, what does
it mean a viable child? So he said if by animals it's
a different story but by human beings once a child is born,
an infant is born, if he survives for thirty days he's no
longer a נפל. nefel. Now by the way that רש"י Rashi points
out that doesn't mean you always need thirty days, that's when you're
not sure if it was a full pregnancy, full term. But if
you're sure it was full term even רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel would say you don't need thirty days. Take a
look at the small רש"י Rashi
four lines down in the wide lines.
No, is that the רש"י? Rashi? One minute. No,
no, more... specifically in ודוקא אם ספקא כלו חדשיו או לא. V'davka
im safka kalu chodshav o lo.
Only if we don't know if it was a full number of
months, full term pregnancy. אבל היכא דכלו לו חדשיו, Aval heicha dechalu
lo chodshav, but if we know it was a full term pregnancy,
תנן במסכת נדה, Tnan b'masechet Niddah, we taught in נדה, Niddah, תינוק
בן יומו פוטר מן היבום. Tinok ben yomo poter min hayibum. As
soon as he's one day old, as soon as he's born, he
gets the mother off if you know, if you know it was
a full term pregnancy.
But Torah's a פטר רחם Peter rechem we have to see.
Okay, so I don't know, that's טעמא דקרא, Taama d'kra, but let's
go to the הלכה. Halacha. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer, כל ששהה באדם שלשים יום, Kol sheshaha b'adam shloshim
yom, so if you don't know if it was a full term
pregnancy, now reading רש"י'ס, Rashi's, you know, qualification, then you need to
wait thirty days to know that the child is viable in those
scenarios where it wasn't full term, and therefore you don't know if
the mother is off the hook for יבום until thirty days have
passed in those cases, right? You got that? You got that? הלא
שהה, Halo shaha, if you didn't wait during that period, ספיקא הוי,
Sfeka havei, it would be a doubt whether the child would be
viable and therefore a doubt whether the mother would be off the
hook of יבום. ואיתמר, V'itmar, and it was taught, מת בתוך שלשים
יום, Met b'toch shloshim yom, now let's say the child died within
thirty days, ועמדה ונתקדשה, V'amda v'nitkadsha,
and she went ahead and she got married. Okay. So wait
a minute, right,
and she assumed that, oh, so here you have this child, right,
that it's during thirty days, we don't know if he's viable or
not. Now interestingly, even though he dies, it doesn't prove that he
wasn't viable. He could have been viable and died for another reason.
So he died within thirty days, the mother assumed, oh my son
died, I can go ahead and I don't need יבום or חליצה,
I can go ahead and get remarried. Okay. She assumed it wasn't
viable, but it's not true, it's a ספק. Safek So she went
ahead and got married and she's in a category still of ספק
Safek having needed חליצה. And I'm sorry. No, I'm sorry. The opposite.
Not she assumed that it wasn't viable. Excuse me. She had a
child. She assumed I have a child, I'm free to go ahead
and get remarried. Okay. Makes sense, right? People with me here? She
has a child, she assumes she's free to get remarried. Okay. Turns
out now, we will know after thirty days whether that's true or
not. The only problem is child died within thirty days. So we
now have no way of knowing what her status was. And if
the child had not been viable, she wasn't free to get remarried.
She would have needed חליצה. Okay. So she really should have done
a חליצה מספק Chalitza misafek and she didn't. She maybe didn't know
better. She got remarried but she needed a חליצה מספק. Chalitza misafek.
Okay. מת בתוך שלשים יום ועמדה ונתקדשה. Met b'toch shloshim yom v'amda
v'nitkadsha.
רבינא משמיה דרבא אמר, Ravina mishmei d'Rava amar, אם אשת ישראל היא,
Im eshes Yisrael hi, if she's now married to a ישראל, Yisrael,
חולצת, Choletzet, do the חליצה now. She needed a ספק חליצה, Safek
chalitza, do it now. ואם אשת כהן היא, V'im eshes Kohen hi,
but if now she's married to a כהן Kohen and she is
a ספק Safek in need of a
חליצה, so אינה חולצת, Eina choletzet, don't demand a חליצה because then
you'll make her forbidden under her husband. So does she ספק need
חליצה? Yes. But בדיעבד, B'diavad, you're not going to demand it if
it's going to mean she can't stay with her husband. רב משרשיא
משמיה דרבא אמר, Rav Mesharshiya mishmei d'Rava amar, אחת זו ואחת זו
חולצת. Achas zu v'achas zu choletzet. No,
he doesn't have any sympathy. Either way, she's going to have to
get a חליצה and if it means she'll have to divorce her
husband, she'll have to divorce her husband. Okay, so that's the debate
there when you have a need of a ספק חלוצה Safek chaluza
and she's married to a כהן, Kohen, are you going to demand
that need or not? So what's the case here when a כהן
Kohen married the woman who was pregnant or nursing and we're saying
they got to get divorced until she stops nursing? Will you demand
that by a כהן? Kohen? So
אמר ליה רבינא לרב משרשיא, Amar lei Ravina l'Rav Mesharshiya, באורתא אמר
רבא, B'orta amar Rava, at night he said, look, he said to
you, he said you, רב משרשיא, Rav Mesharshiya, said you needed חליצה
in both cases. He said you know what? You heard that from
רבא Rava at night. באורתא אמר רבא הכי. B'orta amar Rava hachi.
ובצפרא הדר ביה. U'btzafra hadar bei. You weren't in the בית מדרש
Beis Medrash the next morning where he reversed himself and said you
don't need חליצה if she's married to a כהן. Kohen. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so he said back to him,
שריותא? Sharyuta? You've made her permissible? יהא רעוא דתשרי אפילו תרבא, Yehei
ra'ava detishrei afilu tarba, let it be God's will that you can
even permit even תרבא, Tarba, forbidden fat, which means like I don't
trust you to say that רבא Rava reversed himself. I heard רבא
Rava say you need חליצה, you're telling me he reversed himself in
the morning, yeah next thing you'll tell me is חזיר Chazir is
kosher. Okay, so forget it. Anyway, so that's the debate, do we
demand חליצה or not? And therefore the question is, what would you
say in our case if a כהן Kohen married this pregnant or
nursing woman, would you demand a גט Get or not? So let's
just read the one sentence question and we'll answer tomorrow.
הכא גבי מעוברת חבירו ומינקת חבירו, Hacha gabi muberet chaveiro u'meineket chaveiro,
here by our scenario, הנשואה לכהן מאי, Hanesua l'Kohen mai, if she
went ahead and married a כהן, Kohen, would we demand a גט
Get there בדיעבד B'diavad in those. scenario. מי עבדו רבנן תקנתא לכהן
או לא? Mi avadu rabbanan takanta l'Kohen o lo? Did they make
a תקנה, takana, did they make a nice, a waiver, an exemption
for the כהן Kohen so that won't so that they'll be able
to stay married or not? And we will return to this question
tomorrow.